#大家好 今天帶王剛兄弟他們一起來 上山上摘那個稔子
Hi everyone! Today we take our buddy up to the hill to pick the, the "nen zi" (rose myrtle fruit).
#那山上那個稔子應該熟啦
The "nen zi" up there should be ready now.
#熟啦 但是這個果子我覺得不好吃
Yea, but I don't think they are good to eat
#不容易吃 不是不好吃
I mean, they are difficult to eat. Not bad to eat.
#要爬一個小時才吃得到
We'll need to hike for one whole hour.
#可以 從這鑽過去
Alright, we can sneak from here.
#這個沒路哦
There are no paths.
#那你走前面
After you
#要直接開路哦
We need to make our own path.
#我們要從這裡爬到山頂上去
From here, we need to climb to the top of the hill,
#上山頂上那個 野果才多
where there are much more fruits..
#從這裡爬
Climb from here.
#上不上得來
Can you make it?
#那個那 這顆[SIC]樹就不要亂拉 這顆[SIC]很容易斷
That, that one, don't grab that tree. It's very fragile.
#沒問題 沒問題
No problem, no problem.
#拉這顆[SIC]來
Grab this one.
#嗯 好
Um, good.
#走吧
Let's go!
#抓到這顆[SIC]就可以上
Just grab this one.
#這裡面會不會有甚麼野獸哇
Would there be any....like....beasts?
#看到你都怕
Or they all run away from you?
#好像也是
Should be...
#大家加把勁啊
Keep going everybody!
#你確定這裡面沒有蛇
Are you sure there aren't any snakes?
#沒有 我在前面
No.
I'm in front of you.
#一般蛇看到我們都怕的
Normally snakes are afraid of us.
#終於上來了山頂
Finally we are here on the top of the hill.
#你看 他們都是軟趴趴的坐在那聊天 不想動啦
See? They are all so wearied that they are just sitting and chitchatting. They don't even want to move.
#我們去摘 那裡面很多的哦
We'll leave them behind. There are a lot!
#你看 這個是茶果子哦
See? This is "cha guozi" (tea fruit)
#我們這邊的茶果子
the "cha guozi" in this area.
#它這個樹很難長的
The tree grows very slowly.
#長了差不多大多年 可能就那麼大一點點
It takes more than 10 years to have this tiny little tree.
#不過這個 它這裡面的籽啊 可以打油的
But the seeds, the seeds can produce oil.
#這個油對那個人體是挺好的
The oil is quite healthy.
#茶籽油
"Cha ziyou" (tea seed oil)
#很少 產量很低的
It's rare. The yield is very low.
#看一下有沒有稔子啊
Let me see if there are any "nen zi".
#摘稔子才是 摘稔子才算是
We want "nen zi". Only "nen zi" counts.
#一個
One
#這裡好紅的也把它摘掉
And the very red ones here too
#還有小的
And the small ones
#產量好低呀 沒有多少個
The yield is so low. Just a few.
#你看這個 好豐滿啊 圓的哦 你看
Have a look at this one. It's round and fat, see?
#很漂亮的哦
It's pretty.
#你看 這個
See? This one is...
#又大又圓哦
big and round.
#嗯 好吃
Um! Tasty!
#一個也不放過
I'm not going to forgo any single one.
#這裡有一個
Here is another one.
#你個 就摘了那麼幾個
See? There are just a few.
#今年的雨水太多啦
It rains too much this year.
#天氣不好 稔子 稔子長得又小
Under this awful weather, the "nen zi", the "nen zi" are small and...
#又小又那個
small and...you know...
#又那個 怎麼說
and you know....I mean...
#又好吃
and tasty.
#你看這個 黑的像炭一樣的這個
Have a look at this one. This one is as dark as charcoal.
#這個是最好吃的
It is the most tasty.
#這個皮不要
I don't want the peel.
#嗯 你看 看皮我都吃掉
Um! See? See that I have even eaten the peel?
#那邊還有 我再去翻過那個山去
There are still more. Let me go to another hill.
#那邊摘一下
We can pick some more there.
#這個 那麼小一點
Here, just a few, a bit.
#對不起這個籃子啊 摘的
It's not fair to the basket...
#你看
See?
#這裡一個
Here is one.
#這裡也有一個
Here is one too.
#沒啦 就三四個
No more, only three or four.
#這顆[SIC]樹 是去年被雷劈過的哦
This tree, has been struck by lightning last year.
#現在死啦
It's now dead.
#它站得太高啦 (這裡不明白村霸是想說樹的位置太高，還是樹太高，字面上看似是位置太高，但又似在說樹太高，以下當作樹太高)
It's too tall.
#山頂上最高的這顆[SIC]樹
It's the tallest tree on the hill.
#被雷劈
Struck by lightning
#雷為甚麼會劈它哦
But why did the lightning strike it?
#為甚麼會劈它 它站得太高啦
Why did the lightning strike it?
It's too tall.
#哈哈哈
Ha ha ha
#不能站太高的
Being too tall is dangerous.
#槍都專打出頭鳥是吧
The nail that sticks up mostly gets hammered down, right?
#對
Exactly!
#你看 今天沒摘多少 就摘了那麼一點點
See? We couldn't pick a lot today, just a little bit here.
#太失望啦 這一點留給家人吃
It's too disappointing. I'll save my portion,
#我就不吃啦
to my family.